Appleton Sturgis papers, 1862-1874 1997ms469
University of Kentucky Special Collections
Appleton Sturgis papers
1862-1874
1997ms469
University of Kentucky Special Collections
0.45 Cubic Feet 72 items
The Appleton Sturgis papers (dated 1862-1874; 0.45 cubic feet; 72 items) consist of 70 letters written by Appleton Sturgis, who served for ten months on a Union transport steamer, the Achilles, in the Peninsular campaign in Virginia and Maryland.
Sturgis, Appleton, 1842-1900
Biographical note
Appleton Sturgis was born June 2, 1842, in Baltimore, Maryland. Immediate family includes father Captain Russell Sturgis, mother Margaret Sturgis (maiden name: Margaret Dawes Appleton), older brother Russell Sturgis, younger brother Edward Sturgis, and younger sister Kate Sturgis. The family’s home residence was located at 164 East 10th Street in Ward 17 District 9, New York, New York. Sturgis' father was involved in the family shipping company, Sturgis, Clearman and Co. The company was owned by Appleton Sturgis' uncle, William C. Sturgis, and George M. Clearman. During the Civil War, Sturgis served as a lieutenant aboard the Union transport steamer, Achilles, in the Peninsular Campaign, which spanned across Virginia and Maryland. In December of 1862, Sturgis was assigned to work for the Ordinance Office at the Headquarter for the Department of the Gulf, New Orleans, Louisiana, serving there for six months. His initial duty was as a clerk for the Ordinance Office, but he was later promoted to Assistant Chief of Ordinance. Sturgis joined the 3rd division of the 19th Army Corps after his service for the Ordinance Office was complete and was injured in the battle of Fort Hudson. After the war, Sturgis married Emily Lamb Elliot and had four children: Elizabeth, Russell, Dawes, and Arthur. Sturgis died in August of 1900.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift, 1997
Scope and Contents note
The Appleton Sturgis papers (dated 1862-1874; 0.45 cubic feet; 72 items) consist of 70 letters written by Appleton Sturgis, who served for ten months on a Union transport steamer, the Achilles, in the Peninsular campaign in Virginia and Maryland. These lengthy letters contain detailed descriptions of military life, battles, strategy, and a variety of hand-drawn illustrations and maps. They also include Sturgis' personal observations of a tour of the ironclad Monitor (Box 1, Folder 19); of President Abraham Lincoln (Box 1, Folder 21); and various military personnel, including Admiral David Farragut, General Nathaniel P. Banks, General Benjamin Butler, General Ulysses S. Grant, and General William T. Sherman (Box 1, Folder 43). Sturgis also describes in these letters the work he does on behalf of his father, obtaining charters and certificates for company ships to be contracted out to the Union. Additionally, the collection includes one telegram and one general release document.
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open to researchers by appointment.
Arrangement note
Collection is arranged chronologically.
Banks, Nathaniel Prentiss, 1816-1894; Butler, Benjamin F., (Benjamin Franklin), 1818-1893; Farragut, David Glasgow, 1801-1870; Grant, Ulysses S., 1822-1885; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Sherman, William T., (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891; Sturgis, Appleton, 1842-1900; United States. Army. Department of the Gulf (1862-1865).; Baltimore (Md.).; Letters.; Maps; New Orleans (La.); Peninsular Campaign, 1862; Soldiers--Correspondence.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Correspondence.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Equipment and supplies.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Medical and sanitary affairs; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Naval operations.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Washington D.C., 1862 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  To Father. The Achilles and crew are scheduled to depart from Washington for an unknown destination. The Townly is to accompany them. Lieutenant Colonel Ingalls is among the crew, and friend of Sturgis. Provides a drawing of boats on the Potomac River, going past Alexandria. The South America was lost on Hay Island upon it's return home. Gives an account of ships, and mentions May Queen, Arrowsmith, State of Miami, Nanshon, and Cononicus. They were fired upon in Alexandria and Sturgis describes what happened. Relays that Major Tiffany, A. Quarter Master, and Major Perry of the 15th Regiment N.Y. wish to be remembered to his father.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Washington D.C., 1862 March 21; Page one of the letter is covered in a mylar sleeve due to poor condition. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  To Mother. The ship and crew are in Washington pending orders, though Sturgis does not think they are more likely to move anytime soon. Barges they were scheduled to tow were deemed not to be sea worthy, and now they only have the pon ten. Mentions Captain Hennessey and the steamer James Guy. All boats ordered down to Alexandria, except for the Achilles and Townley. They were ordered to take on Gen. Franklin’s division to Fortress Monroe. Pistols fired off every morning like the Fourth of July. Sturgis took time to see his cousins and aunt. Has not seen the Illinois, May Queen, or South America in a while, and supposes they are lost.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Washington D.C., 1862 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  To Mother. The Achilles and crew were docked in Alexandria, and scheduled to be ordered away Tuesday. Sturgis went to visit the city, and the Achilles sent away to retrieve barges in his absence. Met Captain Wilson of the Nanshon and watched regiments embark on the ships Metamora, John Brooks, Nanshon, South America, C. Vanderbuilt, Arrowsmith, and Kennebeck. Gen. Smith’s division and a few thousand of McDowell’s men were among those who left. Sturgis makes the aquaintance of Captain Lopes, and discovers the Achilles should be back before night, so he decided to wait on the Golden Gate, but went aboard the West Kent first to see Captain Kirby. Met a Mr. Clearman, son of Mr. C. on board the War Kent. Mr. C. is likely George M. Clearman of Sturgis, Clearman, and Co. They eventually took a dispatch boat to Washington and met the Achilles. May Queen reported to be at Fort Monroe, the South American reported to have left carrying troops, and the Illinois, Long Branch, and John Farrow reported to have arrived safely.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard Achilles, Chesapeake Bay, VA., 1862 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  To Father. Travelling along the Chesapeake River, just passing Smith's Point on the way to Fort Monroe. Towing three schooners, the Mary Anna, Dan C. Higins, Joseph Home and brig J.W. Drisko, carrying a total of four companies of artillery; part of General Porter’s division. Ordered to follow steamer Washington Hunt. Anchored at Swan Point to allow the Washington Hunt to pass them due to its slowness. Sturgis met some soldiers from the Pennsylvania regiment in one of the schooners. The Achilles eventually overtook the Washington Hunt and towed them with the rest of the boats, and arrived at Fort Monroe. Illustration of how the Achilles towed the seven vessels.
- Letter to Edward Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Potomac River, VA., 1862 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  To younger brother, Ed. The Achilles is on its way towards Alexandria pulling two brigs and three schooners. While they were at Fort Monroe on Wednesday there were about 200 other vessels anchored. Toured the iron clad Monitor, and mentions the Atlantic and Vanderbuilt. Sturgis had hoped the Merrimac would show up, but it did not. During their stay at the fort, Sturgis took time to see the Union Gun and Lincoln Gun, which were pointed towards Norfolk. Describes four gunboats they passed in the bay.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Alexandria, VA., 1862 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  To Mother. Sturgis writes about friends, relatives, and their whereabouts and doings. The Achilles is at the docks awaiting orders. A letter came via Lieutenant Colonel Ingalls, who gave it to Major Tiffany, who gave it to Capt. Hennessey, who finally gave it to Sturgis. Inquires about photograph from Addie Foster. Captain Francis of the May Queen visited the Achilles and went with Captain Andrew. They passed the Arrowsmith going down the river loaded with troops bound for Fort Monroe.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, entering the Chesapeake Bay, VA., 1862 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  To Mother. The Achilles is on the way to Old Point with a tow. There was a heavy snow while they anchored at Mt. Vernon. They were delayed in their travel due to having to tow the Dency and three schooners: the Jas. Johnson, West Wind, and R.S. Dean, as well as two barges: the Wallkill and Cedar Hill. Sturgis mentions seeing the steamship Constitution coming out from Alexandria, after obtaining General McClellan and his staff. Describes the cost of goods in Washington and what he has been spending.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, anchored below Fort Monroe, VA., 1862 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  To Father. The Achilles left Alexandria with heavy tow and arrived at Fort Monroe. Q.M. Captain Hunt sent them off to assist the steamship Constitution, who had run ashore on the Potomac. They then proceeded up the bay to Smith’s Point to locate ship, and met the Constitution. Relays news that the Flushing sunk March 28 or 29. Mentions seeing May Queen, Arrowsmith, Illinois, Townley, Nanshon, John Brooks, Elm City, John Farrow, Daniel Webster at Fort Monroe. Most ships had troops on board and bound for Hampton.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Potomac River, travelling to Alexandria, VA., 1862 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  To Mother. Travelling along the Potomac, just off Indian Head, on the way to Alexandria. Nine or ten heavy guns were fired at Achilles from the shore north of Cherrystone Light, towing five schooners. Sturgis thinks it was possibly a U.S. Union battery who mistook the Achilles for the enemy. The Cononicus was stranded, and the Achilles with the State of Miami and Atlantic try to pull out the ship with no success. Afterwards, they took the Handy, Malony, and three schooners in tow with them to Alexandria. Sturgis located the 20th Massachusetts and meets with friend, Nate Hayward.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Alexandria., 1862 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  To Father. A rumor that rebel troops are nearby is circulating, and the Union only has 30,000 troops in Alexandria under General McDowell. General Hooker’s division is ready to move out in four days to the mouth of Rappahannock. The Elm City, C. Vandervbuilt, John Brooks are located on the Maryland shore of the Potomac waiting for troops. Sturgis reports that General McClellan has 130,000 troops to march to Richmond, and he suspects there will be a fight at Norfolk. Describes finances, payment for crew, and repairs that will be done to ship.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Shipping Point, VA., 1862 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  To Mother. Arrowsmith, Elm City, C. Vanderbuilt, John Brooks, Croten, Sea Shore, and R.J. Spalding transporting troops and on the way to Alexandria to get more. General McClellan and 60,000 troops have rebel forces surrounded and trapped near Yorktown. General Franklin’s division started to arrive, and gunboats are waiting up York river. Sturgis describes the 100,000 men and wagons that stretched four miles long, the conversation he had with men from the 69th New York about their movements, and General McClellan’s narrow escape from a rebel trap. He also lists the acquaintances he has made that may be useful for his future in the shipping business, and some of the jobs the Achilles and the crew have been doing. Transcription of a copy of an incident report.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Alexandria, VA., 1862 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  To Father. Around 300 boats waiting in the river waiting for troops, including the Constitution. Sturgis describes his visits with family: Aunt Kate, Aunt Lottie, and Uncle Charles. General Franklin’s division leaves the city to go support General McClellan, and Sturgis describes their send off, including the band and songs that played. He also discusses the strength of the rebels in Yorktown, possible battle strategies or siege, and the troops high opinion of General McClellan. During this time, one of the crew members lost a toe in an accident while oiling the engine.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Washington D.C., 1862 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  To Mother. Sturgis left the Achilles for a few days to finish up business about the charter for his father, and is staying at his Aunt Lottie’s residence. Describes what he has been doing while on land, and asks after the rest of the family and whether they dyed eggs for Easter Sunday.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Washington D.C., 1862 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  To Mother. Sturgis mailed his father the certificate and charter, and telegraphed to inform him. Visited the Capitol, President’s House, Patent Office, and Smithsonian Institute. Relays that Richmond may be won before Yorktown. General McDowell is marching upon Richmond, while General Franklin and General McCall are at the mouth of Rappahannock to march across the York river. Describes possible military strategies, and issues they may face with rebels.
- Letter to Edward Sturgis, Washington D.C., 1862 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  To younger brother, Ed. Sturgis is waiting for the Achilles to return, and estimates 7-10 days passage from Alexandria to Ship Point or Fort Monroe. Writes about fishing, the price of fish, and life on the Seim. Asks about friends, including one killed at Pittsburg Landing, his older brother, Russ, and Uncle William. Requests to be sent fishing hooks, and provides a drawing of the hooks he wants.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Washington D.C., 1862 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  To Mother. Sturgis expects the Achilles to return that day, and is travelling to Alexandria to meet it. Complains of life on shore, and his desire to be back at sea. Acquainted himself with the Captain of the Saturn. Visited cousins, Callie and Emma Kassen, and Aunts, Kate and Lottie. Wrote a personal letter for a deck hand who could not write. Asks about new clothes and handkerchiefs.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, at the docks waiting for Achilles,Washington D.C.., 1862 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  To Father. Preparing to travel to Cape Henry. Sturgis describes his dissatisfaction with the ship’s cook and requests that his father send them a better one from New York. Sturgis is unsure of what the ships movement will be, since orders are given on very short notice. The boiler blew out, and had to be repaired. The ship's whisky supply ran out at Ship Point, and Sturgis sent a request for more. Father approved of certificate.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Chesapeake Bay, VA., 1862 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  To Mother. The Achilles will be at Fort Monroe by tomorrow. Sturgis attempted to find a new cook in Washington, but had no success. The ship was ordered to tow several vessels bound for Hatteras: Condor, Susan Duncan, four schooners G.C. Morris, Dean G. Higgins, Maryland, and John Farrow. The vessels held troops for part of Van Allen’s, 3rd New York Cavalry, and the Achilles is scheduled to stop at Fort Monroe to pick up soldiers from General Wools to reinforce General Burnside. The Achilles is currently under the order of Lieutenant Colonel Mix and staff, who are aboard the John Farrow. Sturgis describes the men of the 3rd N.Y. Cavalry, and how they drill and spar on the decks of the ships. While the ship and crew were anchored at Piney Point, they took leisure time and ate oysters.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Fort Monroe, VA., 1862 May 4-5 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Hatteras, NC., 1862 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  To Mother. Achilles is named Flagship of the Hatteras Expedition. They were ordered to drop their tows at Cape Henry, and then return to Ft. Monroe, however Colonel Mix requested to have the Achilles under his orders for a while longer, and the ship and crew will continue to follow the orders of Colonel Mix. Sturgis transcribed a copy of the order the ship and crew were given.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Fort Monroe, VA., 1862 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  To Mother. Sturgis just returned from Norfolk, which was taken by Union forces. The Achilles was ordered up to Norfolk shortly after the city was taken, and was the second ship to arrive after the Victory. As the ship travelled up Sewells Point, they passed President Abraham Lincoln aboard the steamer King Phillip. The crew gave the president three cheers as they went by, and President Abraham Lincoln took off his hat and bowed. Sturgis describes the celebration when they arrived in the city, and the view of the guns on Canary Island. Upon passing the Monitor Sturgis found out from the crew that the Merrimack was sunk just below Canary Island. Sturgis describes what the crew of the Monitor said about the battle that occurred as well as the look and price of various food items after going ashore and the appearance of the city.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Fort Monroe, VA., 1862 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  To Father. The Achilles is in the process of coaling up for a trip to Baltimore, and will be towing the Nelly Baker to repair leaks after it ran ashore. Richmond was taken and the city surrendered to the Monitor and Galena. The rebel army is in a trap. The news may change the direction of the Achilles, and they may possibly be sent up river towards Richmond. Sturgis assures father he will work on getting a second charter certificate.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Hampton Roads, VA., 1862 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  To Father. The Achilles received official written orders to tow the Nelly Baker to Baltimore and report to Major James Belger to receive barges, but they were delayed until the next day. Sturgis spoke to Captain Thomas about the certificate, and he will go from Baltimore to Washington to get the certificate while repairs are being done to the ship. Sturgis goes on to further discuss charter business and dates. The crew is getting homesick, and Sturgis does not think they will stay after their contract months are up.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Chesapeake Bay, VA., 1862 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, Chesapeake Bay, VA., 1862 May 15-16 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  To Father. May 15: Currently in the Chesapeake Bay, and Captain Andrews arrived safely. Sturgis will pay some of the crew tomorrow and discusses the possibility of getting new hands to replace those that leave when their time is up. Notes that all mail going to Old Point is opened by the Provost Guard, and lists things he needs to purchase for the ship. May 16: Sturgis arrived in Baltimore, reported to Q.M. Major Belger, and then went to the government ship yard to have boiler repairs on the Achilles, which should take two to three days. Sturgis requests more money from father and lists his expenses. Will send a telegraph to father explaining where to send money.
- Telegram to Captain Russell Sturgis., 1862 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  To Father. The telegram reads: City Department, American Telegraph Company, General Office, 145 Broadway, with a disclaimer and the charge amount for transmissions underneath. Received at the New-York Hotel, May 16 1862. From Sturgis to his father requesting money be sent to him via Mrs. Burnaps. The back of the telegraph features a map of New York City Stations for the American Telegraph Co.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, Baltimore, MD., 1862 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Baltimore, MD., 1862 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, White House, VA., 1862 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, White House, VA., 1862 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  To Father. Several boats have been sent home. The Achilles will be sent up James River eventually. Major Belger made a request for the ship to be sent to Baltimore. Sturgis has not heard much news about the other ships, only the May Queen and Herald.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, White House, VA., 1862 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  To Mother. Sturgis volunteered as an A.D.C. with Mrs. Balestien and Iriss Bradley, friends of his mother’s, on board the Elm City. Remarks that tending to wounded soldiers is not appropriate work for ladies and discusses learning how to do his own laundry. Weather has been hot, and the water is making the crew sick.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, White House VA., 1862 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  To Father. Sturgis decided to stay aboard the Elm City and help with the wounded. Relays to father that Mr. Weed is returning home, and apologizes for the delay. More boats are returning home; the Secor and Nantucket have already gone, and the Pioneer, Columbia, and Catskill will follow soon.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, White House, VA., 1862 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  To Mother. The sick men were moved from the Elm City and only the very sick were not moved. Sturgis attends a soldier's funeral, and upon returning received orders from Colonel Ingalls to move all men aboard the Knickerbocker. Describes the confusion from none of the men knowing how to proceed, which forced Sturgis to take charge and give orders, and was then appointed Ward Master. He lists some of the remedies given to the soldiers, such as brandy punch, milk punch, beef tea, and explaines how they were administered. The Daniel Webster arrived from New York safely.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the floating hospital ship Knickerbocker, White House, VA., 1862 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  To Mother. The United States transport and headquarters of the sanitary commission, currently laying the Panduskey River, two miles below the White House, VA. Sturgis thinks the patients have seen good results from his nursing, and believes many of the patients will be sent home. Visited the Achilles while it was being painted.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, White House, VA., 1862 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  To Mother. Sturgis describes nursing and watching patients all week and lists things he needs from the commissary stores. The crew of the Achilles went aboard the Daniel Webster to prepare it for sick and wounded men to be brought aboard. Head of Commission, Mr. Olmstead, and Dr. Knapp headed the project, and ordered Sturgis to act as Quarter Master. Sturgis describes the surgeons, doctors, and ward masters on the ships for the wounded. He also provides a copy of the list given to Dr. Knapp regarding the preperations, and provides names of people from New York he met while working. Sturgis asks his mother to remember him tomorrow for his 20th birthday.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, White House, VA., 1862 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 36)